Friends with Brews Clay Daly, how are you?
Splendidly well, how are you? I'm good
I was gonna say this would be a second episode in a row with a guest and not with Peter
But that wouldn't be true because I recorded an episode with Peter
Earlier this week that's gonna go in between. Oh
Yes, Peter in between the two right the Peter sandwich and I feel like it's important for his morale that I
Allow him to think that I still care about him and so I'm gonna keep that order
Well, hey, listen, the sandwiches are go well with tea, don't they or brews? Yes. Let's talk about your tea
What do you got for me? I got a it's a sort of you know how chai is often a lot of times
They happen with low caffeine, but I got a black chai with it's a chai tea mixed with like black tea and
The cardamom is hitting me hard. It's lovely lovely notes of cardamom. Do you have a brand?
This brand is the tiesta tea t ie s ta I normally go to Whole Foods
I can't usually get the Whole Foods brand but okay
You remember the Teavana days when Teavana was still a thing
I used to go get their stuff and then of course Starbucks decided to shut them down, but whatever
No, I'm bitter oh
Oh, so this is do they have multiple so that here's a spice chai black tea. Is that a different one than the one you have?
Yeah, no, that's the one. That's the one I have spice. Yeah, it's really good actually. Nice. That sounds good
I may have to get that. Yeah. What are you what are you what are you brewing over there? I have a coffee
It's from I called it. They're a local
Roaster I call them Coava but it's co ava so Coava might not be the right pronunciation
But this is called S.O. Blend. And I don't know what S.O. stands for. It's S.O., so it means something.
Anyway, they describe it as "The Americas and East Africa Rich Chocolatey."
This has honeycrisp apple, dark caramel, and chocolate-covered fruits. And it's really smooth. I like it.
Chocolate, you said?
Yeah, chocolate.
Nice.
Yeah, Honeycrisp Apple Dark Caramel Chocolate. The thing is the flavors aren't super strong,
but that's what I like about this brand is even with my particular pour-over method,
I don't have to try very hard at all to get a nice, smooth, very non-bitter cup of coffee
with this brand.
Nice. One day I may try coffee.
You know what? Don't because it's… I mean, I could… if I wanted to, I could kick the
caffeine habit, I would just hate it for two or three days.
But if you're not addicted to that much caffeine, why do it to begin with?
If you can function without it, don't do it.
I mean, coffee is enjoyable, but it's probably not worth getting addicted to the caffeine
over.
Although small amounts of coffee are supposed to be...
Like people do drink small amounts of coffee when they're doing like endurance activities,
but then too much is the opposite effect.
It'll make you jittery and it'll affect your performance.
Right, right. True.
And I get jittery enough just from work.
Yeah, same here. Yeah, so I probably don't, I don't eat coffee. I'm jittery enough.
Yeah, exactly. Jittery enough. That'll be on my tombstone. Should never have had coffee.
Was jittery enough?
Yes.
Okay, so what is going on in your podcasting life these days? I've seen, I've seen instances
of you recording with people that look photographically involved.
Yeah.
So my co-host, Devon Warren from MVP, Most Valuable Photography Podcast,
him and I, we actually, you know how they say you're supposed to be consistent
to make this work, right?
Well, that's what we've been trying.
And it actually has been working every other week.
Imagine that, Clay.
Yeah. That's cool. Good. So for people that want to listen to that, where can they find that?
All the podcatchers just look for most valuable photography podcasts. And you'll find us. I think
MVP might bring it up to. I think it does in Spotify, at least, which is, you know, the devil.
But yeah. Okay. Looks like is that still on Anchor? I found an Anchor link.
Yeah, it is still on Anchor. Yeah. Okay. Nice. Yeah. Nice. Yeah, I only have one show on Not
the anchor and that is the cyber cash which is technically on a break but it's a very
long break. It's a season. You're in between seasons. Yeah, yeah, yeah. You know like the
budget you know we can't come to the terms you know stuff like that. That's true yeah.
There's some egos at stake and people need salaries that are outside your capability
right now. Yeah they want more than zero dollars so yeah. Yeah I get it yeah. Luckily for me
me, Peter has never asked for more than zero dollars.
Good. Yeah. You guys have a good, you guys, this show is good. You guys have a good dynamic.
I like it. Thank you. It's good energy. I hope Peter enjoys the dynamic as much as you
do. I don't know. There was one day, I can't remember what it was. Oh, he was going to
bring something up that I absolutely did not want to talk about. And then he was like,
I thought it was fair game since you always roast me on this podcast every time. And I'm
I do? So that made me have to re-examine myself.
Well, a little bit of roasting, I mean, for a brew show is pretty good, isn't it?
Yeah, I think so. Why not?
I mean, Vic used to get roasted by us every now and then.
That's right. If we can roast our coffee beans, I can roast Peter's bean. I'm talking about
that.
There you go.
Not... wow, okay.
Beans. Peter, you meant beans.
That went lower than I thought. Yeah. I don't want to know about Peter's
Light Roast. So I have not talked to you in a long time, honestly.
>> Last time was on a podcast. Last time was "Bubblesort" or did I just say "Bubblesort"
or yeah. I know that seems like a show that doesn't exist, but yeah, there's a show
called "Bubblesort" and yeah, that's the last time we spoke, right?
>> Are you a subscriber to the Multiverse Theory? Because I'm thinking it did exist,
maybe people in this... maybe it's one of those Bernstein-Bears things. Maybe it
kind of existed, but now it doesn't, and it never did now. I don't know.
You know, you might be right. You know what? I jumped universes. I'm in the wrong one.
I apologize. The sad thing is all of the the US political situation seems to be
the same in every universe I keep helping you to. It's not getting better.
Not getting better. Unfortunately. But what camera gear... what are you using for cameras right now?
know, like on a typical basis or what are you getting into recently that I haven't
known about?
Well, I mean, you know, still shooting the moon actually, which is something that I need
to do more of because I drive to work early in the morning and then I see the gorgeous
moon up there. And you know, like I make my schedule, right? Like I can go into work at
any time I want. So I technically should just walk with my camera, which I do sometimes
to work, but I should walk into work with my camera and take, just pull over and take
pictures of the moon which I have done way in the past but work is kind of hectic so
I haven't in a while. But yeah the main camera is a Sony a7R IV which is a beast of a camera
with 61 megapixels. I mean no one really needs 61 megapixels do they?
Well people throughout the history of humanity we've always said nobody needs this that and
the other but it sure is nice. It is nice. It is nice. Are you shooting any?
No, I haven't for a long time. No. There's a lot of different A7s, aren't there? There
are, yeah. I mean we have the R which is resolution. We have the S which is the video line which
is, I think S stands for sensitive because they have sort of better sensitivity in low
light. And then they have the plane which is just, you know, it used to be 24 and now
I think it's 33. And then they have, then they moved off of just being 7s and then they
went to a nine and then they went to a one. Yeah. You know these companies with their
numbers. They love their numbers.
I know. Yeah. And they always go backwards for the better cameras, the smaller numbers.
Yeah, they do. Even though the funny thing is that so you have the A7, right? Then you
have the A9, which technically, technically is a better camera than the seven line because
it's like a A7 but like on steroids. And then they decided, you know what, we're going to
follow a Nikon and Canon and decide to go A1 which is like the beast of beasts.
Oh my God. I'd hate to…I'm looking at the A7R right now, A7R IV and I don't…I
got to…oh my God. I'm afraid to look and see what the A1 costs.
Yeah, trust me. And the thing is that the A7R IV cost what it costs. You know, I mean
I got honored a deal actually but…and that's the only reason I picked it up honestly. I
I'm not doing this for a living, right? So I'm not going to go crazy spending that sort
of money. But it wasn't cheap. But it wasn't as expensive as you see now. But then they
had the A7R5 and that's even more expensive. Inflation, these companies love to use this
as an excuse for, "Hey, guess what? Things do cost more." But do they cost that much
more?
Yeah. Did they cost that much more and do the prices never go back down again? That's
the thing about like once pandemic hit, everything, like think about food, how much do you spend
any time you go out now? Like we can't go out, just the three of us as a family, to
any, and I'm not talking fancy restaurants, I'm just talking like good, like we went for
Korean the other night, and it was a good restaurant, good Korean food, but three people,
yeah, okay, we had quite a bit of food and we took some home, but it wasn't like we stuffed
ourselves senseless and it was 100 bucks. I mean, that's just standard now. And I feel
I feel like a lot of the other companies have taken whatever minor supply shortages they've
had and they've amped up their prices.
Like Mirrorless, I thought Mirrorless would help the prices.
Far from it.
I think cameras are way more expensive than ever now.
Yeah, yeah.
Because the thing is that we went to Mirrorless and the prices were a little bit higher than
they should have been.
But you're like okay it's new technology, we'll allow it. And then all of a sudden you
know the pro cameras and the non-mirrorless side you know like a regular SLR, DSLR type
of cameras. The pro cameras are costing crazy money but it's a pro camera. Now you're going
over pro-sumer on the mirrorless and they're matching the prices of the pro side on the
DSLR. Like you know they pulled the fast one on us because technically yeah it's supposed
to be cheaper to make them. It's supposed to have less moving parts and therefore it's
supposed to last longer and somehow it doesn't. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, it's crazy. I don't...
I mean, photography has always been a hobby that you could spend a lot of money if you
wanted to, but now it seems a little bit insane. Like I still have my old Nikon, Nikon, whatever
everyone call it, and I would love,
I like the kind of camera that you have.
I like that very much.
And I think, like I wasn't criticizing or judging you
for the price of that camera at all.
I think it's a beautiful camera.
And I think that's the kind of camera I would love to have.
And there's no way that I can,
until my daughter gets out of the school situation
she's in, there's no way I could ever even think
about something like that now.
Whereas previously I could possibly do it, yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, like, so if I hadn't gotten the position at work that I had now, I don't
think I would have. It would have been like, hey, nice, but not now. Eventually, like,
I mean, my first A7, I have two A7s. I have a regular A7 and that was also sort of more
than I wanted to spend, but it was a deal still, right? Like, so I wait for the deals,
right? You know, everyone always jumps on things when they first come out. Like, I wait
things. Because could you imagine if you buy something right away and then you're like,
oh, snap, this thing is a lemon? Like, I don't want to be that person, you know.
Right. And that way, later on, you have the option of getting something that's been refurbed,
getting something used. You have a lot more options.
Definitely.
And even if the price goes up slightly or remains the same and you decide to buy new,
well, that's your choice and you came to that decision by waiting and thinking about it.
Yep. Like right now, I'm actually thinking about adding a second body because, you know,
when I do shoot like portrait sessions or you know something like that. My two cameras
are the A7R IV which is at 61 megapixels and then my old A7 which is 24 megapixels. But
the issue is that the old A7 system autofocus is just not up to speed. And you know like
back in the days DSLRs had a slight advantage over mirrorless cameras in terms of auto,
manual focusing, but they don't now because of the punching. You could punch in now. But
you know old school film cameras had an even better advantage because you had like all
these sort of different prisms that you could put on your camera that would help to aid
with manual focusing. I don't have that with my old A7, especially because the viewfinder
is really low resolution. And then on top of that, the autofocus is no good, right?
>> Yeah, the viewfinder, I remember the viewfinders used to be problematic. And even on DSLRs,
they weren't great, but it didn't matter as much. But then once you got to mirrorless,
it started being a bit of a pain for a little while.
>> Yes, yes. It's better now because you have giant megapixel counts in like the Canon high
end line, the Nikon high end line, and Sony high end line. They all have, you know, giant
megapixel account, you know, little L is basically a little, you know, big screen
TVs inside of the viewfinder versus what we used to have.
For sure. Yeah.
Yeah, it's kind of weird.
Like before the pandemic, my father in law,
I feel like he went and bought another DSLR.
He upgraded. He bought a better Nikon DSLR than what he had.
And I kind of I don't know if he cares about mirrorless or not.
I don't I don't know what his thinking on that topic is,
but I kind of think I would never do that right now.
I would never do that again, I don't think.
Oh yeah. I don't see the point in it.
To me, that seems like, first of all,
part of photography is it is absolutely about the photos.
Who cares what the camera is,
as long as you are having fun taking the photos
and you're learning how to get results that you like.
But camera gear is fun.
And those old DSLRs, they don't excite me at all,
not a bit anymore.
And I think that's why I couldn't imagine
spending the money on those anymore. Yeah, no, I'm with you. Like if, so let's say, let's
say if I were doing this for a gig, like actual money, right? And I'm doing sports, I could
see myself actually going to get a high end old DSLR for the sports. Right? Because you
like a high end DSLR is definitely going to be better than a mid range like Sony A7 or
Nikon Z6 or something like that for sports. If you can get the high end, you know, we're
talking about like Canon 1D or Nikon D3 or D4, right? I could see that. But if you can
afford to go like Nikon, you know, like Z3 or, you know, Canon R3, if you can afford
it, you'd be better off if you actually are shooting sports. Everything else, I would
just be fine with like a regular A7. You know, it would be perfectly fine. But when we're
talking about sports, sports that I have, you know, are still at the high end of demanding,
i have tried to shoot it, you know, and Chidgey shoots it. and, you know, he could tell you,
you know, all the struggles. I mean, it's not easy, you know. So, yeah.
Yeah, I agree. I mean, yeah, for sure. There are certain jobs where, I mean, you do have
to, if you're a professional, your job requirements and the ability to do the best job are going
to be the primary factor in determining what equipment you'd select for sure.
For sure, yep. But no matter what I did, even if I was back into shooting again and I did
it every day and I dreamt about it all the time, I wouldn't even get to the point where
I would be an interesting amateur. So I could pretty much pick whatever camera gear I wanted
within my budget, which is quite limiting.
There's a lot, you know, like there's a lot of, especially if you're okay with use, right?
people for some reason don't want to buy used cameras. I don't get it. But there are people
who are always upgrading and you could find someone locally and say, "Hey, you know what?
I know you're selling this camera for 500 bucks." And I've done this, right? I've actually
bought, I just bought like a lens that's like a, like it was, so when Sony went from the
A-mount, which is the DSL, which is, they actually never had a DSLR really. They had
an SLR, SLT, which is like a translucent mirror inside. It was like an in between between
in a DSLR and mirrorless.
So they had that system, and that system was the A mount,
which is the Kanaka Minolta old mount that they bought.
They bought Kanaka Minolta.
So that mount still has a great set of lenses.
And so I bought an adapter for my Sony A7,
and actually I found a person who was selling
this 135 millimeter lens that is brand new.
I think it was like $2,000.
And I think he was selling it with a bunch of stuff
for like about a thousand dollars, and I just offered the guy like 450, and he said, "Yeah,
I'll take it." You know? And so I got this amazing lens that just I got for nothing.
I mean, people are just wanting to get rid of this stuff sometimes. So like if someone
sells something for 500, just say, "I'm not low-balling you. I have 400. Will you
take it?" You know? And if they say yes, you have nothing to lose. If they say yes.
That's true. Yeah. You're just some random guy. If they hate you for the rest of your
lives, that's their problem.
So be it.
No, I don't know.
I know that in the old days, I remember a lot of people
didn't wanna buy used camera bodies
'cause they were always worried about shutter actuations.
And then lenses, people are always like,
well, you gotta make sure that lens isn't scratched.
And before the internet, it was a lot easier
'cause typically you were gonna go see the thing in person
before you ever bought it.
Right.
And I get not wanting to, but man, especially for lenses,
just frigging buy used.
Like you said, you can get some amazing lenses.
And if you're doing creative type photography and speed is not of the essence,
who cares if it, you know, you can get some amazing lenses that produce
interesting results that they may not necessarily work with your autofocus.
They may have certain features that don't work, but who cares?
Mm hmm. I agree.
Yeah, I mean, I have a giant, you know, cabinet behind me here with a whole bunch
of old lenses that I used to lost after from, like, the film days that now are crazy cheap.
And yeah, it's not the easiest to use on again, some of these cameras, but just patience and
a tripod sometimes will do the job.
And fun. It's interesting. It's fun.
Oh yes, definitely.
That's cool.
Definitely.
What about film? Are you doing any film these days?
Well, so the internet is actually losing their mind about film at the moment because the
prices have gone berserk.
I can imagine. Yeah, yeah. So for right now, I think film is really meant for pros right
now, personally. For me to spend the amount of money on film is a little bit like looking
at a camera that is $2,000 and looking at film and doing film for a year, you probably
will end up spending about the same amount of money including the camera, right? Yeah.
And that's one year.
That's crazy.
Yeah, it is pretty crazy.
Like the prices of film right now are pretty high.
And the thing is that like, yeah, I develop at home myself, but guess what?
I don't have the time for it.
So I would, if I were to shoot, keep shooting film and you know, the only film I shoot right
now is actually instant film, which I love.
But if I were to keep shooting film, I would have to devote myself to actually developing
at home, which I don't, I don't at the time.
scanning at home, which I don't have the time, and doing calibrations on the frames that
I've got, which I don't have time. I don't have time for these things. And then the money.
The money is not like, for me, it's like, I'd rather just spend the money on some lenses
and have a nice lens for my Sony. Or I have actually a bunch of cameras. I have the little
One Series Nikon One Series, you know, like the one inch cameras, which are nice for shooting
the moon because you can put like a regular lens on there and have basically you know
2x zoom because of the sensor being so small.
Adam Boffa Like if you were new to developing your own film and it was novel and it was
fun and exciting and you were willing to say I'm gonna really reduce the amount of time
I have for actually shooting and buying camera gear with you know reduce the amount of money
I have for camera gear but it's worth it to me because I'm gonna learn how to develop
this film, that would be one thing, but you already know how to do it.
And it's probably not the most exciting part of photography for you.
No, it's not. It's not.
It's exciting because you're like, snap, I'm doing this, right?
Like people pay for people pay someone else to do this.
But guess what? It's not that much money to pay someone else to do it.
But, but, but, but there's a big but it does add up, right?
You know? Yes. So that's the problem.
It's like how much money are you going to say?
You say, oh, it's still it's cheaper than digital.
But does it though? Right? Because it adds up. I mean, if you do this for two years, how much money did you spend?
Versus how much that digital camera cost?
It's almost like back when I was a kid and I wasn't paying for my own stuff.
And I would either have to scrimp together money to develop film or my dad was going to be paying for it.
And so I had to be very careful. It really limited the amount of shots that I could take. Super.
And it's almost like that again with film.
Yes, definitely like that. Yeah, definitely.
That's, it's too bad. That is the one thing about digital, whatever you think about film,
whatever you think about digital. First of all, people get amazing. You know, I think the biggest
appeal of film is that it requires a little more work and that you can get different results with
it. But I think it's more about enjoying the process than anything. But that is the one
advantage of digital. Immediately when digital came along I realized, "Oh my god, I can
shoot however many photos I want and some of them can be terrible and I'm not going
to feel bad about that because, you know, aside from the fact that nobody wants to shoot
99% terrible photos, but I'm not going to feel bad about that because it's not going
to cost me a thing." And the film was never that way for me.
No. No. Unless you're rich.
Right, exactly. In which case you're too busy buying property in New Zealand or whatever they do these days.
Or maybe giving Elon Musk all your money in case he establishes a Mars colony.
Oh, gosh. That guy.
That guy.
I don't get it.
I noticed you still use... Do you still use Twitter?
Yeah, yeah, I you know, the funny thing is that I
so
Mastodon like I'm trying to use it, but it feels like it feels like it feels kind of clicking
I know what you mean
it's much less so for me now than when I started and I think one thing that really helped was a
huge influx of people who didn't care about the stupid rules like
There were so many Mastodon-splainers early on. Here's how we do things here. Here's how you must do things.
And it's like, listen,
I get that you have a culture you like and I get that there are certain ways that you do things that may or may
not be better, but
Clay, every time we've gone to a new social network, it's always our "don't stink," right? It's always that way. And it's not true.
It's never true. It's just people. There's no
group of people that's so much smarter and better than other people that they've developed a perfect social network,
but they always think they do in the infancy of these social networks.
Yeah.
And there was a lot of, you know, explaining going on on Mastodon,
but my attitude was I'm going to ignore these people,
and when enough other people come in that ignore them too, it won't matter anymore.
And for the most part on my Mastodon, I don't see a lot of the posts anymore saying,
"Welcome to Mastodon. Here's our 24,000 rules that you must abide by."
Yeah. Yeah.
But I will say that I follow a number of Black people on Mastodon that still highlight a
lot of the issues, which is a lot of those rules around content warnings and a lot of
the rules that were built up for people who don't want to see certain types of content,
they hinder necessary and productive discussions about racism, even unintentional racism, and
how is it ever going to improve if you want to silence those conversations because you
think that belongs behind a CW?
And I think that's one of the biggest problems with Mastodon is it was so monoculture for
so long that it really, it left a bad taste in my mouth when I first started using it.
And I'm like, man, these people don't get it.
They don't understand.
Like you can't lecture to other adults how to use, you know, you understand that the
people coming in here are grown adults, right?
you're trying to tell them how to have conversations, that just doesn't work.
It doesn't, no. So is that still a thing, the whole CW stuff, or is that minimized?
I think it's way minimized. And also, I've been on the Ivory betas for a while. Like,
I have the iOS beta, and now I finally got on the Mac beta. And for a long time, because
they were just building it on the fly from the bones of Tweetbot, I guess, it didn't
really show the CW, it didn't really handle CW very well, it just showed you everything.
And now, even on the web now, I see a lot less CWs than I used to. So I think that due
to multiple reasons, people just aren't using CWs that much anymore, because the CW culture
was ridiculous in the beginning. Like, I get that there's people who don't like eye contact,
but like there would be a photo of a cat looking into the camera and people would put it behind
a CW because the cat was making eye contact.
Yeah, yeah.
You can't expect everybody to be that... I mean, I don't know where you draw the line,
but to me that's way on the wrong side of it.
Well, that's why I kind of... So I post a picture of something and I'm like, "Okay,
am I supposed to put it behind the filter? Because I'm not sure. Like, what if the moon
is mooning me? Like, oh, this moon is mooning me. Like, this is offensive. Like, I don't
know." You know what I mean? So it's kind of like, right.
You know, some people might be werewolves and they're trying to control it. And you
you show them a picture of the moon, Clay, and they're going to have a problem.
It's like they're banging in the middle of Starbucks because of me. Geez.
I'm sorry.
Yeah. Where's the content warning, they howl?
Yeah, I know. Yeah.
So that sort of stuff kind of made me just a little bit,
I don't know.
For sure.
Just nervous. I'm like, okay, I'm going to come in here. You know,
there's Twitter ref... I guess that's offensive too, Twitter refugee.
but you know, Twitter outcast and coming in here and posting pictures that I
think are perfectly fine. And then I offend someone because I just mooned them.
I don't know.
From what I've seen, and at least on the server that I'm on.
So basically what I see on my home view is stuff that's on that server.
And it's on that server because people follow certain people.
You know what I mean? Like everybody's view is going to be different.
But the view that I see, I don't see a lot of that anymore.
It's way less than it used to be.
And I think, you know, I'm a white middle-aged dude.
There's very little I'm gonna see
that is probably going to cause a problem for me
because people's inherent biases
that Mastodon was built around
are probably more like mine than not.
But even having said that,
I see a lot less of the CW culture, the lecturing culture,
the here's how we do things on Macedon culture.
I don't know where those people went in despair,
but I feel like a lot of them have finally realized,
hey, these grown adults have come in here
and they're gonna talk how they're gonna talk.
That's the thing about social networks.
They've never ever been used exactly the way
even the creators envisioned.
Yeah.
They just don't.
People come in and they find the way they wanna use it
and that's how it gets used.
Yeah, and the thing is that a lot of times creators,
see something that we, the users, do and then they're like, "Wow, that's brilliant.
We didn't think about that. Let's add that."
Like, the whole quote-toot thing was a huge controversy for a long time and it's like,
"Guys, yes, it can be a magnifier, but you guys keep saying that Mastodon is built specifically
so that individual things can't go viral as easily. So therefore, you can't use a quote-toot
to dogpile as easily as you can on Twitter. So why not let it happen? And then also, you
can be an ass to people in replies already. Like it's, it's not like that's the only way
you can ever harass somebody. So we can't allow it. But we can allow these other things.
No, harassment comes in all forms, including silencing of discussions of racism by saying,
Oh, that belongs behind a CW. That's harassment, too.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And that actually, that is actually a very good point is that,
you know, if you decided that something was perfectly fine and someone else,
one person decides that, you know, that this is offensive to them, it's, I mean,
like, again, you can't please everyone, right? Like, and the social media,
it's, I don't know, I don't know why we call it social media because it feels
very antisocial. Yeah, antisocial media. Yeah, you know, I don't know. I don't get
that offended by a lot of stuff. You have to go really far to offend me, okay?
Well, here's the thing. It's like, everyone is going to have triggers. Like, we all have
had things happen to us in life to where things that other people would never imagine would
be painful for us to hear are going to be painful for us to hear.
Yeah, true. And we as humans, there is a line. We as humans
have got to, this is just part of growing up and as culture evolves and as new technologies
come on or new use cases evolve, we just have to figure out where's the line that makes
sense so that we're not purposely being jerks to people and just saying, oh, that doesn't
matter. Like people who get mad because they can't be a certain way anymore. And it's like,
no, we're not trying to stifle you. We're just asking you not to be dicks. Is that such
a hard thing? But then there's also the thing of people who want every personal trigger
of theirs accounted for, and you can't do that. And so, like, for example, I know people that have
had their children die. Are they going to get mad and get offended whenever anybody at work
is talking about their kids? I'm sure it's incredibly painful. But they can't. And I'm
sure that if people who know them and know their story, they would probably be careful about what
what they said around those people. But people who don't know, and they're standing there
talking about their kids, which people do all the time at work, that would be amazingly,
incredibly, devastatingly painful for those people to be reminded that, "Hey, they're
having these happy experiences with their child, and I'm not." But they're not going
to jump on that person and attack them. Not unless they're super unreasonable, right?
They can't. Because part of life is other people have kids.
Yep, we'd hope so.
So there has to be, yeah, there has to be, you know, when you yourself are feeling pain
from some of the things that people are talking about, you have to be willing to honestly
engage in an internal dialogue of saying, "Is it reasonable that these people are allowed
to talk about this, or are they just being dicks?
Or are they just being normal humans, and this is part of the human experience?"
And yeah, this hurts for me, but I'm not going to ask them not to do that because there
are times where it's unreasonable for them to do it, and there's times where it's unreasonable
to ask them to stop doing it.
Is it easy to figure that out?
No, not always.
But you have to at least be willing to admit that that's the case.
Yeah, that's true.
Probably a dumb example.
No, no, that is a good example, though, because the thing is that normal people will, on one
side realized that, yes, guess what? This is going to be a thing that happens to me.
I lost my child and this is something I have to deal with. And the opposite side, you know,
people lose kids. But like you can't, you can't put everything behind the content warning
just because you're like snap, like, okay, my son just like did this amazing thing and
I can't talk about it because someone might have lost a child. Right? So that is a very
good example actually.
And I'm not saying that we should not be cognizant of other people's needs and feelings.
Right.
At all.
And it is a tricky—it is hard.
Like it is hard, but there has to be—there has to be—like, you know, if people wanted
to they could hear what I'm saying and they could say, "Oh, well, you know, that could
allow for a lot of racist things," and people could say, "Well, that's just how humanity
is.
This is just part of being society."
Yes, it could.
it used to, and it still does in a lot of places.
And so I get that, but I'm saying,
that's why I'm saying you have to have the rule of,
are you just being a jerk,
or are you just being a normal human being?
It's an evolution.
There's a lot of things that we know now
that we should not do or say because they are wrong,
and we did not used to think they were wrong.
Right, right.
I don't know, it's hard.
Being a human is hard, Clay.
They're very hard.
Maybe we shouldn't be humans anymore.
Well, I think we're on our way out, aren't we?
I think so, yes.
I think this may be a solved problem.
It just hasn't completely gotten there yet.
Right, exactly.
Oh my God, did you notice?
And I knew this was gonna happen.
I figured it was only a matter of time,
but now this avian flu is jumping to other animals.
Oh my gosh.
Yeah.
It happens, but geez, gosh.
Oof.
Yeah.
Painful.
It is painful.
I look, I'm not. I do eat meat. I do eat chicken and fish.
But I tell you, I just buy the whole meat industry is horrible.
It's abominable. It's a large part of what's killing the planet.
Yes, it is. Yep.
We go overboard with stuff like, you know, oh, guess what?
There's gold in the ground. We're going to overmine.
Oh, there's, you know, the animals have Omega-3.
We're going to over fish.
I mean, yeah, we go overboard.
Right. Most of what we do, if we did in moderation, it would be okay.
And if we did it in a balanced way, it would be okay.
But you're right. We go so overboard.
Part of it is just how many people live on the planet.
But part of it also is just capitalism.
Capitalism is engineered that way.
And I feel like in the United States,
we still hold on to capitalism as such a religion.
Very true. It is a religion, though.
Capitalism is just a system. Yeah, it is a religion.
It's just a system, and I don't understand why so many people think this is the inherent good way.
This is the... Look, I understand that you can look around and look at communist countries
and look at socialist countries and say, "Look at all these problems."
But look, we're capitalist, but if we get an authoritarian in place, you can have bad people in charge in any system.
And it's true that a lot of communist countries have authoritarians in place.
And a lot of the people I know that have escaped from communist countries and come to the United States are very conservative as a result.
But you can have authoritarians in place in a democratic, which isn't really anymore, and a capitalist society, and it's just as bad.
And it might even be worse because then you have all these corporations that are taking advantage of you at the same time as the authoritarians are ruling you.
So I just, I really wish humans didn't have such a bias towards the way things are.
Like we have a tendency to think, "Oh, this is how it is, so this is the way it has to be."
When all, everything we do, everything we see, everything we think is all made up by us.
And it doesn't have to be that way.
It's not inevitable, but it's only inevitable because everybody thinks it is.
Right.
It's a chicken and egg.
Chicken and egg, yeah.
Cycles.
And both the chicken and the egg have avian flu, by the way.
Yes. Is it because the chicken ate the egg and then the chicken laid the egg and then
the...okay, never mind. Cycle.
Probably.
Sneaks. Tails. Something like that.
The chicken ate the egg. The chicken laid an egg, which might be the same egg or have
parts of the same egg. I don't know. It gets weird. I don't understand animals. How do
they even...oh, boy. I don't know. We all see what we want to see out of life.
Yes we do. So I mean I know this is giving Elon too much credit here but maybe we might
actually be in the matrix.
You know some of the things that are happening, I don't believe it but some of the things
that are happening are the best indication of it that I've ever seen. You can't make
this stuff up. It is almost like somebody's tweaking a bunch of sliders to see what would
happen.
Yeah. How far can we push it? Oh my gosh did someone see it? Pull it back, pull it back,
pull it back.
Yeah exactly.
out. They saw too much. How dumb can we make these people and at what point do they actually
kill themselves? Yeah. There seems to be, and I don't know why, but when people get
a certain platform, Elon Musk is one of these guys, but you know that a lot of his, like
he has become very Donald Trump-like in his tweets and his stupid sayings and just the
dumb things he says and does. The way he communicates, it's very childish and Trump-like. And
And I gotta say, I'm starting to wonder if giving some of these people who don't have
normal social interactions, they're billionaires, they're rich, and/or they're technically influential
in the tech industry, and so they don't have a lot of people pushing back on their really
stupid ideas.
And I wonder if giving these people a platform and telling them that they're right about
everything is what makes them that way.
So it is interesting to me that there is a phenomena of people
converging towards this type of personality once they get a big platform.
It can't be coincidence.
Mm hmm. Well, still someone like him becomes rich, right?
And so they've been convinced by their actions and their
people who are under them that they are always right.
Yeah.
So people like that, you can't tell them anything, right?
I mean, I don't know, I mean, honestly, if Steve Jobs had bought Twitter, what would
we, you know, I know that we can't, you know, people keep pulling Steve Jobs out of the
grave, but I mean, you know, would he have been the same way? I don't know. I mean, Bill
Gates, would he have been the same way?
No, and I think those guys were formed in a different era, though. They certainly had
their own problems. They certainly went from, they certainly went, well, in the case of
Bill Gates, he never really proclaimed
the hippie culture so much, but Steve Jobs,
like many quote, counterculture people at the time,
certainly became diehard capitalists in a heartbeat.
Yes.
But those guys came of a different time,
and I think they already were established enough
in their own personality.
I think that's one of the benefits of not,
I think that's one of the benefits of the past,
where as you're growing up, as you're developing,
or as you're becoming,
for these people that are influential, becoming influential,
you don't have the same huge platform
where you're a performer.
And I think the performance aspect of it
is part of it that amplifies this to some degree.
I don't know how much, but I think it does make it worse.
Reality TV was an indication a long time ago
that when you take people and put them on a stage,
they become dumber than ever.
Yeah.
And now you're doing it to billionaires who never,
at least on reality TV,
other contestants or other people on the show would say,
"You are the biggest idiot I've ever seen."
No one ever says that to billionaires.
(laughing)
Oh, and that's one of the other downfalls
of our capitalism religion, Clay,
is that like you were saying,
they think they're right about everything.
Absolutely, because we have this inherent belief
that if a person is a billionaire or even a millionaire,
they must know things that we don't know.
They must be smart about everything.
It's not that they had one specific, it's not that they had also good luck,
but it's not that they had one specific area of knowledge or one domain that
they're good at. No, they're good at everything.
We have to listen to them about everything they say.
Yeah. Yeah. No, I mean, so, so people like,
people like Elon, I mean, look at, look at someone like Andrew Tate, you know,
with his, I mean, they get, they,
they get these cults following everything that they say and defending them at
every turn, right? I mean, you say anything about Andrew Tate and about him getting
arrested and all of a sudden you get attacked by a bunch of bros. I mean, they
are bros usually because, oh, you know, he needs to be proven guilty. And it's like,
okay, right now he's in jail for his alleged, you know, crimes. Like, why are
you going to go out of your way to defend someone? It's all because, according to
people, they have made it, right? And so someone who's made it, you're going to blindly follow
them because hopefully one day you'll fall into their footsteps. You're not going to.
Sorry. These people are… I don't know if you follow anything that Andrew Jates does,
but he actually is one of these people who can convince people to sort of throw money
at him and say, you know, I will teach you my way, you know. And it's like, people who
can't afford spend money on things like this hoping that one day they will be as rich as
Andrew Tate. And it's like, yeah, the reason why Andrew Tate is going to keep being rich
is because suckers like you are born every day who are going to give them money, right?
It's like they don't realize that they're the bones that are feeding this machine or
whatever the term is. Same thing with the Paul brothers, Logan and whatever his other names.
Oh my God, yeah.
Yeah, I mean just abhorrent human beings who are able to convince people to throw money at anything they do, right?
You know, the whole cryptocurrency space has people just losing their minds and their money at an alarming rate.
And it's only because again we like to put people on pedestals and
you know if Elon Musk were to say here's a
Course it's a ten thousand dollars for the year
There are gonna be a lot of people who are gonna pay for it
You know and I mean just because he made it doesn't mean you'll make it too. Sorry, you know, sorry to burst your bubble
But I think that's the fear here
Do you think it's gotten worse though how much we need people need a hero people need somebody who can
You know be their answer
Do you think it's getting worse or am I just seeing it more because the internet dumps everything in our face
It really seems like now our culture just wants we just want an answer. We don't want it to be complicated
It doesn't matter if they're an authoritarian if they have an answer for us
It's all good. Is it worse or is it just that I'm getting old and I'm getting tired of humanity?
Sometimes I feel like it's getting worse and and the thing is that it's I think what it is is not that it's getting worse
Is that it's just more televised right or more
Broadcasted I think it could be a we elevate the negative
Yeah, we do. All right. I mean the thing is that like we've had
Can't believe I'm gonna say this, but we've had
I'm not comparing Elon to Hitler here, but I'm saying like we've had people like Hitler
come to power and people, you know, I mean, I mean, he was sort of lifted on a pedestal,
right? People like that happen. It happens. If it was happening during our time now, like
he would have had a far broader audience. You know, I mean, you know, he had Germany
an audience. I mean, in Poland as audience, but now it's like, you know, you become someone
like Elon. And again, you know, please, listeners, I'm not comparing Elon to Hitler. Like I'm
just stating, you know,
You're talking about the cult of personality phenomenon.
Exactly.
How people like that can become influential.
Exactly. Right. Yeah. Yeah.
And nowadays, I hate to say it, Clay, but I don't think the Republicans would push back
on Hitler all that much.
You know?
I don't think you're not far off here.
I mean, look at this country.
They're trying to ban everything now.
We're becoming a "here's how you must behave."
It's like Macedon used to be, except these people have power to make laws happen.
Yeah.
Content warning, content warning.
There's a Black History...
Content warning.
I mean, the whole Black History month thing is pissing me off, too, because this...
I've seen some of the most ridiculous things.
You know, like, I mean, in Miami, they have a cop car that was covered by all sorts of
like, the Shiki, you know, all this sort of African, you know, tribalist stuff.
And it's like, like, how about you guys figure out how not to kill Black people, maybe, you
know?
Right.
Because that's not helping, is it?
Well, maybe all their cars should be covered with that.
Maybe they, maybe those cars would not, maybe nobody would, maybe police wouldn't want to
roll up on the scene in one of those cars and then jump out and kill a Black guy.
So maybe that's part of the solution. Cover them all.
Maybe. But yeah, it's ridiculous. Yeah, it's insane. It's like, really? You guys are their
allies now? I don't get it.
I mean, the thing is that everything is about the whole publicity thing, right? Yeah. But
it's like, if you like, I want action. I don't want, like, show. Show. There's one thing
to say something, but there's one thing to do, right? Like, do, don't say, you know,
Like actually don't kill people instead of saying we're going to kill less people.
And they don't say it, but like the whole implication of this car covered in this African
stuff.
I mean what is that trying to, what are you trying to tell us with that?
Like why are we wasting our time with this?
And that even goes to, you know, like people like me or other people who say, "Oh, we are
a hundred percent understanding of what Black people are saying and we are on their side."
But then, if Black people come to the conclusion that they're not getting results and they're
tired of being killed, and they're going to do something that might be construed as disruptive,
like protesting a certain way, or they might want to fight back against the police, then
even people who call themselves open-minded and liberal are going to say, "Oh, no, no,
that's wrong.
That's not how you do stuff."
Well, guess what?
It is how you do stuff when you're not getting results the other way.
Yeah, you can't talking until you're blue in the face and then it doesn't do any good after a while
You can't live with that anymore. You know, I when I was younger. I didn't realize that but I
get it now and I'm you know, I
Sometimes if you're right, you got to do what you got to do. That's that's how that's the realization I've come to and I
I'm not here for I'm not here for people saying yeah. Yeah, we get it. But by the way, nothing's ever gonna change
I don't I'm not here for that anymore. Mm-hmm. It's made this place what it is and it's not it's not working
Nope, I agree
It isn't
Humans are super flawed. Yes, we are my
Co-worker Yuzuf. He says we went to watch
2001 at a local theater here that has a gigantic
beautiful old analog projector on a gigantic screen and
And they got a special cut of 2001 made just for them. That was the Space Odyssey 2001. Yeah. Oh nice
so his
His quote about humanity is never should have touched the monolith
We knew that that's our motto we never should have touched the monolith
That's good. That's spot on. That's good. Oh, that's good.
I don't know. I have no answers. I don't know if anybody does have answers.
No. We all pretend to have answers. We don't have answers.
I think the best we can do is try to honestly operate out of good faith instead of—
Yep.
What amazes me is how many people are just willing to blind, you know, openly and clearly
take advantage of other people.
You know, aside from humanity's always been horrible towards each other.
All the people we've killed, all the people we've tortured, all the people we've enslaved,
all the horrible, horrible, horrible things we've done to each other.
It's like, how can you, how can you even do that?
But then even just on a daily routine basis, taking advantage of other people, building
systems in place that we get people to root for and cheer for that are actually taking advantage
of them. But we shouldn't end on this note though, this is bad. Oh, you know what, I want to play a
clip. This is hilarious because Peter Nikolaidis is an IT consultant and a security guy,
But for some reason, he will readily admit he's like a walking EMP.
He breaks everything.
I don't know how.
I don't know why.
But he has problems with his technology that I've never seen before.
Huh? And I was listening to the Six Colors podcast the other day,
and they were talking about Dan Moren and his co-host on a podcast that he has.
And it reminded me of Peter.
So I'm going to play this.
For those who don't know about Guy English,
He is a lovely man. First off, I, I, when Dan referred to his friend Guy English,
I thought he was making it up because that is not a real name.
My imaginary friend Guy English.
Guy English. It sounds so fake, right? It's a phony, fake name. Anyway, he's a real guy.
Gay name Guy.
And real English.
And he's really English. He was born in England.
He was born in England. That's true.
Now he's Canadian, but he's also English. And very, very smart guy. He worked at Apple.
He's a software developer. He's, you know, he does, he, he and Dan talk,
and Moltz spent five years on an island talking about Arrow.
It was rough.
And you guys do the Biff podcast now.
He's like got a negative podcast energy field around him.
It's a thing.
I wanna describe, can I describe,
while we're in the after show here,
can I describe the tech profile of the Biff podcast
in my own words, which is,
there's Dan, a professional podcaster
who has a professional podcasting setup. Okay, seems good so far, right? There's John Moltz,
who, I don't know if he still does this, but for a long time, his podcast recording strategy was,
he talks to you from one computer and records his audio from a different computer, because
neither of his computers is trustworthy enough to act on their own. And then there's Guy. And Guy,
You know, again, very technical, very smart guy.
Somehow, like, I don't know, he records in echo chambers,
where he's down in a well.
-I've been to his apartment and his office now,
and it's a small windowless room,
and it really is just, like, an echo chamber.
-And then there's also roll a die
to see if the recording works.
-I will say, the funny part of this is,
is since I went on parental leave,
Guy has edited Biff for the last, what, six months.
And so I don't have to deal with those problems currently.
So I just like, well, you know,
and I think it's actually helped because he's like,
"Oh, now I can hear what I sound like."
So he has improved, I think he got a new mic,
and I think we put him on an ATR or something
was a little less room noisy.
'Cause he had some really weird audio setup stuff.
Whatever his microphone he was using,
he had some connectivity issues with the microphone,
which there was some where it dropped out,
and then you had to use the backup tracker.
There was one where he sent me the laptop mic recording.
It's been bad luck with Guy.
So anyway, have him on live on Discord.
What could go wrong?
I hope Jason Snell doesn't sue me,
because that's a members only podcast.
But I only took two and a half minutes of it, so I think I'm okay.
Yeah, it's a good way to spread the memory.
Go, everyone, go sign up for members only podcasts.
That's right.
Six Colors, yeah.
But that just reminds me of Peter a lot.
And it does remind...
Now, I will say one thing about Peter.
When I first started podcasting with him and through several different podcasts, I had
so many issues with his recording.
It was just like that.
Sometimes he would send me a recording from the wrong mic.
Sometimes he has gotten a lot better.
Now it's always the correct mic, his recording always works, it sounds a lot better than
it used to, and when there is a little bit of background noise, it's stuff that I can
easily filter out now.
So I recently, whatever he did recently, and I think he improved it when he started recording
Blurring the Lines with Adam, but I gotta say, Clay, you are the one person, as far
as I know, when you started podcasting, you just figured it out. And ever since then,
it's just worked. You don't come with the wrong mic. You don't have, you know, crickets
chirping in your studio.
I was just gonna say crickets.
Yeah. I don't know how you do it. But you're the type of person that should be podcasting.
Jeez, wow. Thank you. Listen, podcasting, you know, I have a solo podcast that actually
is supposed to come out of hiatus forever, but podcasting is fun when it's like with
friends, you know, like this is fun. Like this is a blast. I enjoy it a lot. I'm the
one, I'm overly technical at work. I'm the guy who fixes everyone's problems at work.
But I don't normally have problems with technology. But again, I also don't have a job that is
just, you know, it's in the medical field. So there are a lot of people who aren't supposed
to be technical in my field because we have an IT department, but usually I am the IT
guy.
>> Right. Yeah. But you also, once you get something working, you don't fiddle with it.
>> No, I do not. No, I do not. That is one thing I do not do. Like if it's working now,
It's like it's cemented in place.
Yeah.
Yep.
And that is one thing that I was worried about when I went back to the laptop as my only
computer lifestyle was.
Like when I had the iMac, the advantage of it was my recording situation never changed.
That thing just sat there and all the stuff that was connected was always connected.
So how do you solve that problem?
Well, it hasn't been an issue.
Once I plug it back in, one thing that I did do though was I have an application from Brett
called Bunch. And basically what it is, it's a little menu bar app and you can
click on a bunch in the menu to run that bunch. And what the bunch will do is it
pops up programs that you want associated with that bunch. So it's like
a session. And I have it do that but I also have it set my audio inputs
and outputs. Oh okay, that's cool. Yeah, so that way I make sure that when I'm
podcasting my output goes to my AirPods and my input is my... Your mic. It's a loopback device,
it's my mic plus the soundboard. Oh yeah yeah okay. And now I do still have to check individual
applications like I have to make sure Discord is set up that way, I have to make sure FaceTime is
set up that way, but if I don't change those, those don't change. And so far it's been pretty
seamless. The only issues I've had are like things that like we had today where I figured out that
Discord couldn't hear me unless I let it adjust the sensitivity. It just didn't know that I was on mic
And that's not unusual every time I podcast with Bart for example in the past
He's always said you're way too quiet. You're way too quiet the last couple times. He hasn't had that issue so
apparently I'll fix that but I do have a
Perennial issue of being too quiet, which is probably not something that you've ever thought about me, but
Apparently computers do
But yeah, it's been pretty seamless. I'm pretty impressed because for all the software, and
it's not like Apple doesn't have audio software bugs.
morale. Yeah, trust me. Yeah.
But so far, it's been pretty seamless. So I've been really happy.
It's been good. Nice. Yeah, I was actually meaning to ask you about about the laptop
setup and because I know that you were iMac, you were podcasting from iMac before. But
Because I know Vic always had issues sometimes with setting stuff up.
Exactly.
And that's part of why I was – every time somebody with a laptop would show up and they
had to fight to get things working, I would be like, "This is why you don't do it from
laptops."
And I would lecture him from on high.
I was the Macedonian of podcasting.
Here's my 4,000 rules.
Content warnings.
Yeah, exactly.
The guy has a laptop.
Oh, no.
He had to plug his mic in.
Content warning.
Don't make eye contact.
But yeah, I've changed my tune.
Oh, okay.
I'm thinking about getting your laptop too. The same one actually because it's actually
selling for the same price you bought it for.
Yeah.
Which is a steal.
It is amazing. It's an amazing deal. It's such a good computer.
Yeah. Yeah. Apple did really well with this.
It's just I open it and it's on. It's quiet. It just does things. The battery is great.
Like my work laptop, of course it's Windows, and it's a good, the hardware is not bad.
It's a Lenovo T14 and I really like the form factor.
It was that computer, like I had a 16-inch laptop at work previously and then I got the
Lenovo T14 and I loved that form factor.
That's what convinced me that the 14-inch MacBook Pro would be perfect for me.
And I gotta say, but other laptops, like you open them and they take a while before you
can do anything.
This computer isn't like that. It's just ready to go.
Same thing with the MacBook Air. I mean, it's crazy.
It is crazy. I don't know what voodoo they're doing. Clearly, they're saving stuff. And
I bet if you hit a certain program instantly, it would be updating in the background. You
might not like if you had an RSS app or something. But everything seems to respond pretty quickly.
It's not like sometimes on iOS, you know how you go to iOS. You know how when you look
at stuff in the app switcher, it's really just snapshots of what your apps were doing
at the time. And sometimes when you go to the apps, all of a sudden you'll see it go
from that snapshot to blank for a minute as it refreshes and starts all over again. It's
not like that with the Mac.
Not like that at all. Nope. I know. I love it. I actually thought that example right
there was going to be the case when I went to M architecture Mac and I was like, "Yeah,
this is going to be probably a little bit painful." And I shocked. I mean, it was amazing
from day one. Because I've had a MacBook Air before, and I loved it form-factor-wise, but
painful to use. And then when I bought this one, I am like, this is what any MacBook Air
should have been from day one. This is amazing. Yeah, it really is. It really is. I've never
enjoyed a laptop so much in my life. I've actively hated laptops in the past because
they were always such gigantic compromises. The only good thing was the portability, but
everything else just sucked so bad.
I just remember getting different cooling solutions
for laptops for use when I was sitting downstairs.
I remember stupid packs that you would throw
in your freezer and then you'd put it on your laptop,
but after 15 minutes, they'd be too warm already
because the laptop would basically burn a hole in them.
Yep, yep, yep.
Now we've gotten, I mean,
so when you look at AMD and what they're doing,
and AMD is doing some crazy, amazing stuff
with their chips,
But none of those laptops are able to do what,
in terms of like portability,
because a lot of them, when you look at the specs,
it's always plugged in.
When it's unplugged, it's a completely different animal,
right, because they have to throttle down like crazy.
And then on top of that,
not only is it throttled down like crazy,
and yeah, the M architecture stuff
is also throttled to a certain degree,
but not to the same level as an AMD chip.
Not even close.
I would say not even close.
Yeah, not even close.
And on top of that, you have crazy fans going.
You have to have giant fans.
You have to have giant heat sinks.
I mean, to a certain degree, it kind of sucks
that the M2 chips have now sort of shrunken
the heat sinks down a little bit.
But it's like, you know, they can even afford to do it
because there's not as much heat.
And when there is a lot of heat,
it still doesn't throttle as much.
Because, you know, back in the days,
Apple would just throttle something like crazy
because there's way too much heat,
these chips are able to run harder for much longer.
I mean, AMD and Intel really like have,
so I mean, you know, when you're having a big gaming system,
that's one thing, but if you're in a laptop,
this is, you know, this is a beast.
It's absolutely a beast.
It's interesting because Apple came to it
from the other side.
They came to it from the performance mobility
and battery performance side.
And of course, I remember standing at work
and talking to a guy and he's like,
"There's no way that a phone chip
"can ever work in a laptop, it's just ridiculous."
And I remember him saying that,
and well, now look at these laptops,
they blow away what there was before,
but they also have the better battery life
and they also are quieter and not as hot and so forth.
But I think the fact that other CPUs came at it
from the other side and they didn't recognize fast enough
or they don't know how to make priority for laptops
so that they don't burn a hole in you.
Like they're still thinking of the plugged in use case,
or they're still okay with battery life
that's only X number of hours.
And like some of those gaming laptops,
their battery will be dead in two hours
if you're running them in decent performance mode
and you're not plugged in.
Two hours, that's a lot actually.
I mean, some of these things are like 45 minutes.
You know, a true gaming laptop with a AAA game,
Like that is like because a lot of AAA games take advantage of everything, right?
Like the whole GPU is completely maxed out, right?
I mean if someone gets a laptop, if someone gets 45 minutes to an hour on a gaming system,
you know, they're happy.
It's like I got an hour of gameplay.
Yeah, that's crazy.
Why would you even bother?
Like at that point you're always going to be doing your, I guess for the times that
you're not gaming but...
Yeah, but even those systems that are for the times they're not gaming, there's no...
Exactly. Because they don't have efficiency cores like the M systems, right? You can actually
use like a 16 incher for like 20 hours if you're actually doing stuff like email. Because
it's not using the – it's not firing up anything but just the efficiency cores, right?
So again, why bother? Unless again, if you're the kind of person who does a lot of gaming
on the fly, meaning like you're not gaming like in a Starbucks, but you're like taking
it to someone's house to go game, right? You're not going to take it home, right? So then
I can understand it.
And I guess nowadays a lot of people are just conditioned to default mentality as a laptop
is a computer anyway.
Yeah, true. True. You know, the only, because you have the studio display, right?
Yeah.
So like because you know like honestly I kind of like I want a studio display and that's
like a lot of me the reason why I want a 14 or a 16 inch is because of the screen and
I would actually stay with the MacBook Air and I'm actually I'm strongly considering
just getting the monitor because I don't have a problem with the MacBook Air. Like
the MacBook Air does all of the work I needed to do. Capture One Pro has no issues on it.
I could have a large session going, no problems. It's almost like whenever, you know, like
think back to whenever you have your iMac when you first got it. It was always crazy
fast at first. It feels like that but still, right? I've had it for, since pretty much
the beginning. Still it's like that, you know. So really and truly a monitor is all I would
need honestly because, you know, like the MacBook Air screen is nowhere near as good
that's your screen. Your screen is phenomenal. Like that is the best laptop screen that Apple
has ever made, period. You know, I mean I see it in the store and I'm like they've
never had a laptop screen that good.
It's just pretty amazing.
It's phenomenal.
Yeah, I think the interesting thing about the M1 architecture is it is good. Like I
bought this laptop not that long before the M2 versions came out, but I have zero regrets.
It's not like I have any FOMO whatsoever and I think this laptop will last me for years,
years and years.
Yeah. I think if people are looking at buying a laptop today and people have asked me, okay,
anyone who is looking at a laptop today, I say go look at the refurbished store because
all those M1s are more than perfect for the next 10 years. Like people are going to be
satisfied with them for the next 10 years. Like you can save a good $800, even $1,000
in some cases if you're willing to do a 512. And the funny thing is a 512 this year in
the M2 is actually slower than 512 of the M1 Pro last year, right? So you win even more
if you actually were to stick to 512 if you were to go to M1 Pro.
Right, yeah, exactly. If you know that if you get the current computer and you're only
going to get the 512, you might as well just get the M1 Pro.
Exactly. That's exactly what I tell people. Because as someone, I forgot who I was talking
but they had just asked me which laptops I get. Me, if I'm looking at it, if I'm going
to 6512, it's M1 Pro. If it's anything above that, yeah, I would consider the M2 Pro. But
then again, like look at the amount of money you're going to spend. You're going to spend
a lot of money. You know, if you're considering what the refurbished store is selling and
refurbished store, I mean, even compared like B&H has a lot of sales, right? And B&H sales
have not even been able to, and usually I always go B&H because I save taxes with them,
because I have a card that they pay me my taxes back. Well, the Apple store has beat
them like for as long as the Mp2 Pros have been out. You're better off buying a true
Apple's refurbished store until they run out.
That is interesting. I will say one thing though. Apple really is stiffing people in
terms of trading stuff in now. Oh my God, don't even bother.
Oh, are they? Really?
Yeah, oh yeah. They give so little money for trade-in devices now, Clay. It's ridiculous.
Oh, that sucks.
Yeah. And it wasn't... I think it was just like this past year or maybe a couple of years,
but before that I've traded in devices and I got enough that it was worth it. But now,
like even fairly recent devices, they're just like, "Oh, that's not worth anything." It's
like, man, you are really devaluing your own products. You know that?
Yeah. Yeah. Because you can actually sell it on like open market for just a little bit
more. Yeah. But, you know, you had to put up with the hassle of dealing with people.
But sometimes it's more worth doing that than to have Apple stiff you on that.
That's not good.
You know what's funny though?
My brother in the past has given me computers that at the time were really good computers
because he hasn't wanted to deal with people selling it privately.
And so he's like, "Here, have this."
Like I had back when the old cheese grater Mac Pro was a thing, he gave me an Alum Mac
Pro once.
He gave me one of the two 27-inch iMacs that I had was from my brother. I mean pretty amazing
honestly.
I'm just like him. Again, why do I have so many cameras? I don't like dealing with people.
I don't want to sell it to any idiots.
I know because you have to worry. You have to worry where do I meet this person? Are
they going to rip me off? And I sold a laptop to a guy in a Starbucks once and I don't blame
him for like he took forever to make up his mind and I didn't blame him how can he know?
How can he know that I'm not some scam artist and I told him I said look here's what I know
here's what I know about the current battery life but at the time those old MacBook Pros at the time
they would develop battery issues where the battery would seem fine and then all of a sudden
it would only last for you know a little while like cells were going bad or something. Oh yeah.
And I told him, I said, "Look, here's my current battery life. It's not as good as it used to be.
The only thing that I'm not 100% certain about with this laptop is the battery. And here's how
long it lasts, but it could be going out for all I know." And I was upfront with him. I was like,
"That would be my only concern if I were you buying this is, is this battery any good?" But
those batteries were replaceable. Yeah, true. Those are good days.
Yeah, they were, but at the same time this MacBook Pro that I have right now could not
be this light and…
No, absolutely not. No, I'll take now. I know a lot of people would probably, you know,
slap me for saying this. I would take the M anything now over anything we had back then.
There's no fans going crazy in my laptop. You can't beat that.
No.
And even if it does go crazy, guess what? It's not as loud.
I wonder what the I wonder if not having removable batteries is better or worse for the environment.
Yeah, that's a good question. That is a good question. Technically, I mean, Apple can Apple
still can replace it, right? Or is it another thing? I think they can if they wanted to.
But I think at that point, it might not be I don't know how much they would charge for
it in a laptop. Obviously, in phones, people do that kind of thing all the time. Right.
But I have never researched what it would cost or if that service is even available to swap the laptop better.
Yeah. Yeah. That's a good question.
I mean, because you're definitely not going to get...
I mean, my MacBook Air is crazy light.
It feels like my MacBook Air from when I had a 12 inch MacBook Air.
And it's, you know, it's about as light as that.
And, you know, so I don't know.
I mean, it sucks that we have to trade certain things for that.
you know, the environment. But I don't know. It's a tough call.
It is a tough call. It shouldn't be, but it is.
I got to admit, I like computers.
I love computers, but I don't like a lot of the things that computers have brought
about, which is destruction of the Earth, use of natural resources.
And then, you know, the Internet itself has caused a whole lot of problems.
Yeah. Yeah.
But then again, like, I have a lot of friends like you
that I would never know without the Internet.
That is true, actually.
I mean, a lot of us, the whole, the four of us, you know, we wouldn't know each other.
I mean...
That's right.
Yeah.
That's a good point.
I'd be a hermit in a cave by myself like I'm, you know, typical clay.
But you're making that sound appealing.
I kind of like that dream.
I'm getting there.
The older I get, the more I want to be there.
Anyway, the four of us can be cavemen together in one cave.
Let's just move to...
Well, don't move to Florida.
Florida sucks.
We've got to find a place that makes sense.
But what happens if Vic finds a way to wire up his kickers?
You know, I think I might put up with that over what we have outside.
Come on.
Maybe.
I don't know about cave kickers though.
I don't want it.
I'm not there for that.
All right, Clay.
I think we should probably, well, I for sure should go back to work.
Yes.
Go to work.
This is fun.
Thank you.
Yeah, it was a blast. Thank you.
Yeah, thank you very much.
What do you want to point people at currently?
What are you... Ooh, I could put you on the spot.
I could make you point people to things and then you have no chance but to come off hiatus with it.
Or no choice but to.
Well, the thing is that the podcast still is sort of like a podcast that can...
You know, it's not like a...
You know, through my lens with Claydee, it's not...
What do you call it? Time sensitive?
Right, it's not time sensitive. Yeah, exactly.
It's evergreen.
Yeah, exactly. There you go. Evergreen. Evergreen. It's Evergreen. Yeah, so people can go check
out through my lens with Clay Daly. they can check out most valuable photography podcast.
I think I might be on an episode of Wobble Sword. I mean, it's still a show, isn't it?
I think it's a show.
Yeah, supposedly there is an episode that will be released.
Yeah. So people can hear me on that if they would like to hear me, I don't know, however
many months ago that was. Talking about who knows what now. Yeah, there you go. So yeah,
and I'm CWDL everywhere. Yes. Maybe I'll mention you on Mastodon once in a while. Oh, cool.
I'm not like Vic. I do listen to, I do check my Mastodon more often than Vic. I will give
Vic credit for one thing though. I told somebody it's going to be a month before Vic sees this
and he saw it like within the same week. So that was actually pretty impressive. He's
upgraded his uh his notification game I guess or something yeah he's either got notifications
turned on which is not how anybody should live or he's got or he just was checking randomly
all right thank you play yeah thank you it's a blast